Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 54: Pulmonary Disorders.
Asthma Acute Bronchitis Pneumonia Tuberculosis Sarcoidosis Cystic Fibrosis Carbon Monoxide Poisoning References During pregnancy, pulmonary disorders are frequently encountered.
In one study, asthma and community-acquired pneumonia accounted for almost 10 percent of nonobstetrical antepartum hospitalizations .
Pregnant women, especially those in the last trimester, tolerate lung disease poorly because of important pregnancy-induced changes in ventilatory physiology .
Lung volumes and capacities are significantly altered.
In turn, these shift gas concentrations and acid-base values in blood.
These important and sometimes marked changes are reviewed in Chapter 4 (p. 66), and normal values for blood gas can be found in the Appendix (p. 1232).
Some of these can be summarized as follows: 1. Vital capacity and inspiratory capacity increase by approximately 20 percent by late pregnancy.
2. Expiratory reserve volume declines from 1300 mL to approximately 1100 mL.
3. Progesterone-driven respiratory stimulation raises tidal volume approximately 40 percent.
4. Minute ventilation increases 30 to 40 percent due to higher tidal volume.
As a result, arterial partial pressure of oxygen (PaO2) rises from 100 to 105 mm Hg. 5.
Expanded metabolic demands cause a 30-percent increase in carbon dioxide (CO2) production.
But, because of its concomitantly greater diffusion capacity and hyperventilation, the PaCO2 is reduced from 40 to 32 mm Hg. 6.
Residual volume diminishes approximately 20 percent from 1500 mL to 1200 mL.
7. An expanding uterus and higher intraabdominal pressure lower chest wall compliance by one third.
This causes a 10- to 25-percent reduction in functional residual capacity—the sum of expiratory reserve and residual volumes.
Beginning at 14 to 16 weeks’ gestation forced vital capacity and peak expiratory flow progressively increase .
The result of these pregnancy-induced changes is substantively greater ventilation due to deeper but not more frequent breathing.
This is thought to be stimulated by basal oxygen consumption, which incrementally rises from 20 to 40 mL/min in the second half of pregnancy.
Asthma.
# Pathophysiology.
Asthma is a chronic inflammatory airway syndrome with a major hereditary component.
Polymorphism genes on chromosome 5q that include cytokine gene clusters, β-adrenergic and glucocorticoid receptor genes, and the T-cell antigen receptor gene are associated with greater airway responsiveness and persistent subacute inflammation .
Racial differences are seen, and morbidity rates are disproportionately higher in black compared with white women .
Asthma is etiologically and clinically heterogeneous, and an environmental allergic stimulant such as influenza or cigarette smoke serves as a promoter for susceptible individuals.
The hallmarks of asthma are reversible airway obstruction from bronchial smooth muscle contraction, vascular congestion, tenacious mucus, and mucosal edema.
Stimuli cause acute infiltration of eosinophils, mast cells, and T lymphocytes.
Inflammatory mediators produced by these and other cells include histamine, leukotrienes, prostaglandins, cytokines, immunoglobulin E (IgE), and many others.
F-series prostaglandins and ergonovine exacerbate asthma, and these commonly used uterotonics are avoided if possible.
# Clinical Course.
Asthma manifestations range from mild wheezing to severe bronchoconstriction, which obstructs airways and decreases airflow.
This lowers the forced expiratory volume in 1 second/forced vital capacity (FEV1/FVC) ratio and the peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR).
The work of breathing progressively increases, and patients note chest tightness, wheezing, or breathlessness.
Subsequent worsening of oxygenation primarily reflects ventilation–perfusion mismatching.
This results from an uneven distribution of airway narrowing.
Varied manifestations of asthma have led to a classification system that considers severity, onset, and duration of symptoms .
With persistent or worsening bronchial obstruction, clinical
stages progress as shown in Figure 54-1.
Hypoxia initially is mitigated by hyperventilation, which maintains the PaO2 within a normal range but lowers PaCO2, creating respiratory alkalosis.
As airway narrowing worsens, the degree of ventilation–perfusion defects is accentuated, and arterial hypoxemia ensues.
With severe obstruction, fatigue causes early CO2 retention and impairs ventilation.
Because of hyperventilation, this may only be seen initially as the PaCO2 returning to the normal range.
With continuing obstruction, respiratory failure follows.
Table 54-1.
Classification of Asthma Severity Figure 54-1.
Clinical stages of asthma.
FEV1 = forced expiratory volume in 1 second.
These changes are generally reversible and well tolerated by the healthy nonpregnant individual.
However, even early asthma stages may be dangerous for the pregnant woman and her fetus.
This is because diminished functional residual capacity and greater pulmonary shunting render the gravida more susceptible to hypoxia and hypoxemia.
Effects of Pregnancy on Asthma Chronic asthma or an acute exacerbation affects up to 8 percent of gravidas (Baghlaf, 2019; Flores, 2020; Mazurek, 2018).
Pulmonary function changes in pregnancy are more pronounced in asthmatics compared with healthy women .
Despite this, pregnancy has an unpredictable effect on underlying asthma.
In a review of more than 2000 gravidas, approximately a third each improved, remained unchanged, or clearly worsened .
Exacerbations are more common with severe disease .
In a study by Schatz and associates (2003), baseline severity correlated with asthma morbidity during pregnancy.
With mild disease, 13 percent of women had an exacerbation and 2.3 percent required admission; with moderate disease, these numbers were 26 and 7 percent; and for severe asthma, 52 and 27 percent.
Others have reported similar findings (Charlton, 2013; Hendler, 2006).
Intrapartum exacerbation rates are controversial.
In one study, 20 percent of women with mild or moderate asthma had an intrapartum exacerbation .
Mabie and coworkers (1992) reported an 18-fold greater exacerbation risk following cesarean versus vaginal delivery.
Conversely, Wendel and colleagues (1996) reported exacerbations at the time of delivery in only 1 percent of asthmatics.
Pregnancy Outcome Asthma remains a potential risk factor for worse pregnancy outcomes despite continued improvements in treatment.
Data from two large studies are shown in Table 54-2.
The incidences of small-for-gestational-age neonates and perinatal mortality also are significantly greater in women with asthma .
However, these findings are not consistent among all studies.
A study of approximately 3000 pregnancies complicated by asthma showed higher rates of maternal pneumonia and cesarean delivery but not of perinatal mortality .
In a European report of 37,585 pregnancies of women with asthma, the risks for most obstetrical complications were not increased .
Blais and associates (2013) noted that the incidence of spontaneous abortion may be slightly greater in women with asthma.
Table 54-2.
Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes in Women with Asthma Some evidence suggests that severe disease, poor control, or both is linked to higher morbidity rates.
In a study by the Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units (MFMU) Network, delivery before 37 weeks’ gestation was not more frequent in pregnancies of women with asthma compared with controls .
However, for women with severe asthma, the rate was approximately twofold higher.
The MFMU Network study suggests also a direct relationship of baseline pregnancy FEV1 with birthweight and an inverse relationship with rates of gestational hypertension and preterm delivery .
Kemppainen and coworkers (2018) found that women requiring treatment for asthma during pregnancy are at greater risk for adverse perinatal outcomes.
Maternal morbidity rises markedly with status asthmaticus and includes life-threatening complications such as muscle fatigue with respiratory arrest, pneumothorax, pneumomediastinum, acute cor pulmonale, and cardiac arrhythmias.
Not surprisingly, maternal and perinatal mortality rates rise substantively when mechanical ventilation is required.
Fetal Effects Animal and human studies suggest that development of maternal respiratory alkalosis leads to fetal hypoxemia well before the alkalosis compromises maternal oxygenation .
Theories hypothesize that the fetus is jeopardized by decreased uterine blood flow, reduced maternal venous return, and an alkaline-induced leftward shift of the oxyhemoglobin dissociation curve .
The fetal response to maternal hypoxemia is lower umbilical blood flow, higher systemic and pulmonary vascular resistance, and decreased cardiac output.
Several studies cited above confirm that fetal-growth restriction rates rise with asthma severity.
Because the fetus may be seriously compromised, aggressive management is necessary.
Monitoring the fetal response is, in effect, an indicator of maternal status.
A return of moderate variability or accelerations in the fetal heart rate is an indicator of improving maternal oxygen status.
Possible teratogenic or adverse fetal effects of drugs given to control asthma are a concern.
Several reports show a slightly greater risk for abnormalities such as cleft lip and palate and autism spectrum disorders, but further verification is necessary (Eltonsy, 2016; Gidaya, 2016; Murphy, 2013b; Wang, 2014).
It is worrisome that up to half of women discontinue essential treatment between 5- and 13-weeks’ gestation .
# Clinical Evaluation.
The subjective severity of asthma frequently does not correlate with objective measures of airway function or ventilation.
Clinical examination also can be an inaccurate predictor, but useful signs include labored breathing, tachycardia, pulsus paradoxus, prolonged expiration, and use of accessory muscles.
Signs of a potentially fatal exacerbation include central cyanosis and altered consciousness.
Pulmonary function testing should be routine in the management of asthma.
Sequential measurement of the FEV1 or of the PEFR is the best measure of severity .
An FEV1 <1 L, or <20 percent of predicted value, correlates with severe disease defined by hypoxia, poor response to therapy, and a high relapse rate.
The PEFR correlates well with the FEV1, and it can be measured reliably with inexpensive portable meters.
It is advantageous for each woman to determine her own baseline when asymptomatic to compare with values when symptomatic.
# Management of Chronic Asthma.
Asthma management by an experienced team produces better outcomes (Lim, 2014; Wendel, 1996).
Management guidelines include: 1. Patient education about general asthma management and its effect on pregnancy (Bonham, 2018; Robijn, 2019).
2. Avoidance or control of precipitating environmental factors.
Viral infections that include the common cold are frequent triggers (Ali, 2013; Murphy, 2013a).
Influenza and pneumococcal vaccination is encouraged.
3. Objective assessment of pulmonary function with PEFR or FEV1 and of fetal status with serial growth ultrasound and antepartum testing if indicated .
4. Pharmacological therapy with appropriate combinations and doses to provide baseline control and treat exacerbations.
Periodic medication reviews are helpful to avoid noncompliance .
5. Treatment of related disorders including smoking, depression, rhinitis, and gastroesophageal reflux .
In general, women with moderate to severe asthma ideally measure and record either their FEV1 or PEFR twice daily.
The FEV1 ideally is >80 percent of predicted.
For PEFR, predicted values range from 380 to 550 L/min.
Each woman has her own baseline value, and therapeutic adjustments can be made using this .
Another described method is a management algorithm using fractional exhaled nitric oxide (FeNO) as a noninvasive marker of airway inflammation .
Asthma exacerbations were reduced by 50 percent with this approach .
Agents for Chronic Treatment Selection depends on disease severity.
No therapeutic regimen for management of asthma in pregnancy is universally accepted .
βagonists help abate bronchospasm, and corticosteroids
treat inflammation.
Stepwise regimens recommended for outpatient management are listed in Figure 54-2.
Figure 54-2: Stepwise approach to asthma treatment.
ICS = inhaled corticosteroids; LABA = longacting β-agonists; OCS = oral corticosteroids.
Barnes, 2018; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, 2007.
For mild intermittent asthma, short-acting inhaled β-agonists as needed are usually sufficient.
Table 54-3 lists suitable agents.
Table 54-3.
Chronic Asthma Treatment For persistent asthma, most inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) are administered twice daily.
The goal is to reduce β-agonists use for symptomatic relief.
Initial low-dose ICS may be augmented to mediumranging dosing if the moderate or severe symptoms shown in Table 54-1 persist.
A case-control study from Canada with a cohort of more than 15,600 nonpregnant women with asthma showed that ICS reduced hospitalizations by 80 percent .
At Parkland Hospital, Wendel and colleagues (1996) achieved a 55-percent reduction in readmissions when severe exacerbations were treated with ICS.
In one study of nonpregnant subjects with mild asthma, as-needed budesonide-formoterol, which is an aerosol ICS and β-agonist combination, was superior to albuterol alone to prevent exacerbations .
This is incorporated in new guidelines .
Theophylline has been used less frequently since ICS became available.
Minimal benefit is gained with these compounds, and they have a high rate of side effects.
However, some theophylline derivatives are considered useful for oral maintenance therapy if the initial response to ICS and β-agonists is not optimal .
Of other agents, antileukotrienes inhibit leukotriene synthesis and include zileuton, zafirlukast, and montelukast.
These drugs are given orally or by inhalation for prevention, but they are ineffective for acute disease .
For maintenance, they are used in conjunction with ICS to allow minimal corticosteroid dosing.
Approximately half of individuals with asthma will improve with these drugs.
However, they are less effective than ICS, and experience with their use in pregnancy is limited .
Last, cromones, which are mast cell degranulation inhibitors, are ineffective for acute asthma.
They are used primarily to treat childhood asthma.
Vitamin D Epidemiological data support an association between vitamin D insufficiency and asthma severity.
The proposed mechanism is modulation of immunological pathways that diminish inflammatory responses .
Jensen and coworkers (2019) reported that pregnant women with asthma have low vitamin D levels.
One systematic review suggested that increasing maternal vitamin D intake might prevent childhood asthma .
Adams and colleagues (2021) reported an association between decreased maternal vitamin D levels and childhood wheezing.
However, a randomized trial with antenatal vitamin D supplementation showed no lowering of childhood asthma risks at 6 years of age .
# Management of Acute Asthma.
Early Treatment Treatment of acute asthma during pregnancy is similar to that for the nonpregnant patient (Figure 54-3).
Importantly, the threshold for hospitalization is significantly lower.
Intravenous (IV) hydration may help clear pulmonary secretions, and supplemental oxygen is given by mask.
The therapeutic aim is to maintain the PaO2 >60 mm Hg, and preferably normal, along with 90- to 95-percent oxygen saturation.
Baseline pulmonary function testing includes FEV1 or PEFR.
Continuous pulse oximetry and electronic fetal monitoring, depending on gestational age, may provide useful information.
Arterial blood gas analysis aides in assessing the severity of an acute attack by providing objective assessment of maternal oxygenation, ventilation, and acid-base status (see Fig. 54-1).
However, Wendel and associates (1996) found that routine arterial blood gas analysis did not help to manage most pregnant women who required admission for asthma control.
If used, the results must be interpreted in relation to normal values for pregnancy.
For example, a PaCO2 >35 mm Hg with a pH <7.35 is consistent with hyperventilation
and CO2 retention in a pregnant woman.
Antibiotics are not given unless pneumonitis is comorbid (p. 962) .
Figure 54-3.
Protocol for management of acute asthma at Parkland Hospital.
aOf predicted value.
bLabor & delivery unit, recovery area, or intensive care unit.
FEV = forced expiratory volume at 1 1 second; PEFR = peak expiratory flow rate (liters per minute).
First-line therapy for acute asthma includes a short-acting β-adrenergic agonist, such as terbutaline, albuterol, isoetharine, epinephrine, isoproterenol, or metaproterenol, which are given subcutaneously, taken orally, or inhaled.
In severely ill women, these drugs can be given intravenously .
Systemic corticosteroids are given early to all patients with severe acute asthma.
One regimen is oral prednisone or prednisolone or IV methylprednisolone in a dose of 30 to 45 mg daily for 5 to 10 days without tapering .
At Parkland Hospital, we use a higher daily IV dose (see Figure 54-3).
Because their onset of action is several hours, corticosteroids are given initially along with β-agonists for severe acute asthma.
If the response is unsatisfactory, a nebulized anticholinergic drug may be added.
These drugs act to relax smooth muscle and diminish mucus.
By nebulizer, a 0.5-mg dose of ipratropium bromide is provided every 20 minutes as needed for three consecutive doses.
Additional doses every 6 to 8 hours can be used .
Also, for severe exacerbations, IV magnesium sulfate or theophylline may prove efficacious.
Further management depends on the severity and response to therapy.
If initial therapy with a β-agonist is associated with FEV1 or PEFR improvement to a level >70 percent of baseline, discharge can be considered.
For the woman with obvious respiratory distress or with an FEV1 or PEFR <70 percent of predicted after three doses of a β-agonist, admission is usually advisable .
Intensive therapy is continued with short-acting inhaled β-agonists, IV corticosteroids, inhaled anticholinergics, and close observation for worsening respiratory distress or fatigue in breathing .
The woman is cared for in the delivery unit or an intermediate or intensive care unit (ICU) (Dombrowski, 2006; Zeeman, 2003).
Status Asthmaticus and Respiratory Failure Severe asthma of any type not responding after 30 to 60 minutes of intensive therapy is termed status asthmaticus.
Generally, management of nonpregnant patients with status asthmaticus in an intensive care setting results in a good outcome.
In pregnant women, consideration should be given to early intubation when maternal respiratory status worsens despite aggressive treatment (see Fig. 54-1).
Fatigue, CO2 retention, and hypoxemia are indications for mechanical ventilation .
In refractory cases, venovenous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) has been successfully used for status asthmaticus during pregnancy (Clifford, 2018; Steinack, 2017).
# Labor and Delivery.
For the laboring patient who has symptomatic asthma, the PEFR or FEV1 is determined on admission, and serial measurements are taken.
Maintenance medications are continued through delivery, and stress-dose corticosteroids are not necessary .
Oxytocin or prostaglandins E1 or E2 can be used for cervical ripening and induction.
A non-histamine-releasing narcotic such as fentanyl may be preferable to meperidine for labor, and epidural analgesia is ideal.
For surgical delivery, conduction analgesia is preferred because tracheal intubation can trigger severe bronchospasm.
Postpartum hemorrhage is treated with oxytocin or prostaglandin E1 (misoprostol) or E2 (dinoprostone [Prostin]).
Prostaglandin F2α (Hemabate) is contraindicated because it may cause significant bronchospasm.
Acute Bronchitis.
Large airway infection is manifest by cough without pneumonitis.
It is common in adults, especially in winter months.
Infections are usually caused by viruses, and of these, influenza A and B, parainfluenza, respiratory syncytial, coronavirus, adenovirus, and rhinovirus are frequent isolates .
Bacterial agents causing community-acquired pneumonia are rarely
implicated.
The cough of acute bronchitis persists for 10 to 20 days and occasionally lasts for a month or longer.
Evidence supporting the benefits of antimicrobial therapy is limited .
As supportive care, cough suppressants containing dextromethorphan and expectorants with guaifenesin appear safe in pregnancy .
Pneumonia.
Infection of the lungs is a leading cause of death in the United States .
Current classification includes community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), which is typically encountered in healthy young women, including gravidas.
Patients in outpatient care facilities develop an infection that more closely resembles hospital-acquired pneumonia (HAP) .
In most cases of CAP, the offending pathogen is not identified.
In a study from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), pathogens were identified in only 38 percent of nearly 2500 adults with pneumonia .
These included viruses in 23 percent, bacteria in 11 percent, both in 3 percent, and fungi or protozoa in 1 percent.
These percentages changed in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic (p. 964).
Half of bacterial isolates were Streptococcus pneumoniae.
Pneumonia in pregnant women is relatively common (Brito, 2011; Sheffield, 2009).
Gazmararian and coworkers (2002) reported that pneumonia accounts for 4.2 percent of antepartum admissions for nonobstetrical complications.
Pneumonia is also a frequent indication for postpartum readmission .
Admission rates for respiratory illnesses during influenza season are higher than rates in the remaining months.
Regardless of etiology, mortality from pneumonia is infrequent in young women.
However, during pregnancy, severe pneumonitis with appreciable loss of ventilatory capacity is less well tolerated (Callaghan, 2015; Rogers, 2010).
Hypoxemia and acidosis are also poorly accommodated by the fetus, and they may stimulate preterm labor after midpregnancy.
Because many cases of pneumonia follow viral upper respiratory illnesses, worsening or persistence of symptoms may represent developing pneumonia.
Any gravida suspected of having pneumonia should undergo chest radiography.
# Bacterial Pneumonia.
Many bacteria that cause CAP, such as S pneumoniae, are part of the normal flora.
Some factors that perturb the symbiotic relationship between colonizing bacteria and mucosal phagocytic defenses include acquisition of a virulent strain or bacterial infections following a viral infection.
Cigarette smoking and chronic bronchitis favor colonization with S pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, and Legionella species.
Other risk factors include asthma, binge drinking, and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection .
Incidence and Causes Pregnancy itself does not appear to predispose to pneumonia.
Jin and associates (2003) reported the antepartum hospitalization rate for pneumonia to be 1.5 per 1000 deliveries—almost identical to the rate of 1.47 per 1000 for nonpregnant women.
Similarly, among 75,000 pregnancies at Parkland Hospital, the incidence was 1.5 per 1000 .
As discussed, at least half are caused by viruses—influenza A and B, metapneumovirus, adenovirus, and respiratory syncytial virus .
A fourth are bacterial, and S pneumoniae causes half of these.
Community-acquired methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (CA-MRSA) has emerged as a common pathogen that may cause necrotizing pneumonia .
Occasionally, Legionnaires disease is encountered .
Diagnosis Typical symptoms of pneumonia include cough, dyspnea, sputum production, and pleuritic chest pain.
Mild upper respiratory symptoms and malaise precede these symptoms, and mild leukocytosis is usually present.
Chest radiography is essential for diagnosis .
Radiographical findings do not accurately predict the etiology, and as discussed, the responsible pathogen is often not identified.
Tests to identify a specific agent are optional .
Sputum cultures, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) tests, serological testing, cold agglutinin identification, and tests for bacterial antigens are not routinely recommended.
Exceptions are rapid PCR testing of nasal swab samples for influenza A
and B and for COVID-19.
An assay to screen for all three is available.
Determination of serum procalcitonin levels did not improve diagnostic efficacy .
Figure 54-4.
Chest radiograph in a pregnant woman with right middle lobe and left upper lobe pneumonia.
Rounded right middle lobe and left apical infiltrates are consistent with the diagnosis.
Management Many healthy young adults can be safely treated as outpatients, and the pneumonia severity index (PSI) and the CURB-65 scoring system are guides to admission .
Neither has been studied in pregnancy, and at Parkland Hospital, we hospitalize all gravidas with radiographically proven pneumonia.
Outpatient therapy or 23-hour observation with optimal followup are reasonable options.
Table 54-4 displays risk factors that should prompt consideration for hospitalization .
Table 54-4.
Risk Factors for Early Deterioration in Community-Acquired Pneumonia With severe disease, admission to an ICU or intermediate care unit is advisable.
Approximately 20 percent of pregnant women with pneumonia admitted to Parkland Hospital require this level of care .
Severe pneumonia is a relatively common cause of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) during pregnancy, and mechanical ventilation may become necessary .
In a review of 51 gravidas who required mechanical ventilation, 12 percent had pneumonia .
Still, their mortality rate is lower than that for other causes of ARDS .
Initial antimicrobial and antiviral treatment is empirical .
In most otherwise healthy pregnant women, bacterial pneumonias are caused by pneumococci, Mycoplasma, or Chlamydophila.
Monotherapy initially is with a macrolide .
Yost and colleagues (2000) reported that erythromycin monotherapy, given intravenously and then orally, was effective in all but one of 99 pregnant women with uncomplicated pneumonia.
During influenza season, we routinely administer oseltamivir (Tamiflu) along with empirical therapy for bacterial pneumonia.
Table 54-5.
Empirical Inpatient Antimicrobial Treatment for CommunityAcquired Pneumonia in Pregnancya For women with more severe disease according to criteria in Table 54-4, Mandell and Wunderink (2018) recommend: (1) a respiratory fluoroquinolone or (2) a macrolide plus a preferred β-lactam .
Resistance of pneumococcal isolates to macrolides will favor fluoroquinolone regimens.
The teratogenicity risk of fluoroquinolones is low, and these should be given if indicated .
If MRSA is suspected, IV vancomycin, 15 mg/kg every 12 hours, or linezolid, 600 mg every 12 hours, is added .
Clinical improvement is usually evident in 48 to 72 hours with resolution of fever in 2 to 4 days.
With improvement, patients can be transitioned to oral forms.
Treatment of uncomplicated pneumonia is recommended for 5 to 7 days total .
Patients should be afebrile for 48 to 72 hours and demonstrate signs of clinical stability before therapy is discontinued.
Radiographic abnormalities may take up to 6 weeks to completely resolve .
Worsening disease is a poor prognostic feature, and serial radiography is recommended if fever persists.
Even with improvement, however, approximately 20 percent of women develop a pleural effusion.
Treatment failure may occur in up to 15 percent of cases, and a wider antimicrobial regimen and more extensive diagnostic testing is warranted.
For example, in some cases, computed tomography of the chest may be necessary to identify empyema that requires drainage.
Pregnancy Outcome Maternal and perinatal morbidity and mortality rates from pneumonia remain formidable.
In five studies with a total of 632 women published after 1990, almost 7 percent required intubation and mechanical ventilation, and the maternal mortality rate was 0.8 percent.
In up to a third of cases of acute lung infection, prematurely ruptured membranes and preterm delivery are frequent complications (Getahun, 2007; Shariatzadeh, 2006).
Likely related to these, older studies report a twofold increase in rates of low-birthweight neonates .
In one population-based study from Taiwan of nearly 219,000 births, incidences of preterm
and growth-restricted newborns and of preeclampsia and cesarean delivery were significantly higher .
Prevention Two pneumococcal vaccines are available—a 23-serotype preparation (PPSV23 [Pneumovax]) and a newer 13-serotype vaccine (PCV13 [Prevnar 13]).
PPSV23 is 60- to 70-percent protective, and its use lowers emergence of drug-resistant pneumococci.
Neither vaccine is recommended for healthy pregnant women.
However, for gravidas with chronic diabetes mellitus or with chronic heart, lung, or liver disease, one lifetime dose of PPSV23 is suggested, if not previously provided.
Moreover, for women with chronic immunocompromise, generalized malignancy, chronic renal disease, cochlear implant, or asplenia, such as with sickle-cell disease, one lifetime PCV13 dose is followed by one PPSV23 dose at least 8 weeks later and then again 5 years later if not provided previously .
# Influenza Pneumonia.
Influenza A and B are RNA viruses that cause potentially epidemic respiratory infection, including pneumonitis, in the winter months.
The virus is spread by aerosolized droplets and quickly infects ciliated columnar epithelium, alveolar cells, mucus gland cells, and macrophages.
Clinical Presentation Each year, 10 percent of pregnant women develop influenza .
Disease onset follows 1 to 4 days after exposure, and common symptoms include fever, cough, myalgia, and chills .
In most healthy adults, infection is self-limited.
Pneumonia is the most frequent complication and mimics bacterial pneumonia.
According to the CDC, infected pregnant women are more likely to be hospitalized and admitted to an ICU .
Others have corroborated these observations (Mertz, 2019; Prasad, 2019).
At Parkland Hospital during the 2003–2004 influenza season, pneumonia developed in 12 percent of pregnant women with influenza .
The 2009–2010 pandemic with the influenza (A/H1N1) pdm09 strain was particularly severe .
In an MFMU Network study, 10 percent of pregnant or postpartum women admitted with H1N1 influenza were cared for in an ICU, and 11 percent of these patients died .
Risk factors included advanced pregnancy, smoking, and chronic hypertension.
Overall, influenza accounted for 12 percent of pregnancyrelated deaths during the 2009–2010 pandemic .
During the 2013–2014 influenza season, a fourth of pregnant women admitted to California ICUs died .
ECMO may be lifesaving (Anselmi, 2015; Saad, 2016).
Rapid PCR testing of nasal swab samples for influenza A and B is available.
Primary influenza pneumonitis is characterized by sparse sputum production and radiographic interstitial infiltrates .
More commonly, secondary or mixed pneumonia develop from bacterial superinfection by streptococci or staphylococci after 2 to 3 days of initial clinical improvement.
The CDC (2007) reported several cases in which CAMRSA caused influenza-associated pneumonitis with a case-fatality rate of 25 percent.
Management Supportive treatment is recommended for uncomplicated influenza, and early antiviral therapy is effective (Oboho, 2016; Wright, 2018).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018a) recommends treatment of all pregnant women with suspected or proven influenza.
This is regardless of rapid influenza testing, which can have false-negative results .
Hospitalization is considered for severely ill women and for those with pneumonia.
Influenza hospitalization rates for those with advanced pregnancy are higher compared with nonpregnant women (Dodds, 2007; Schanzer, 2007).
Treatment is with neuraminidase inhibitors, which interfere with release of progeny virus from infected host cells and thus prevent infection of new host cells.
The preferred agent is oseltamivir (Tamiflu), which is given orally, 75 mg twice daily.
An alternative is zanamivir (Relenza), which is given by inhalation, 10 mg twice daily.
Recommended treatment duration with either is 5 days.
Last, peramivir (Rapivab) may be given as a 600-mg IV dose over 15 to 30 minutes.
All shorten the course of illness by 1 to 2 days, and they probably reduce the risk for pneumonitis (Belgi, 2014;
Muthuri, 2014).
Few data guide use of these agents in pregnant women, but the drugs are not teratogenic in animal studies and are considered low risk .
Recently, the endonuclease inhibitor baloxavir marboxil (Xofluza) was approved for use in nonpregnant individuals but is not recommended for pregnant women.
Prevention Vaccination against influenza A is recommended by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b) and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2019a).
During the 2018–2019 flu season, the CDC reported that only half of pregnant women received the influenza vaccine .
In a recent survey, however, O’Leary and colleagues (2019) reported a 10-percent vaccine refusal rate in office practices.
Any inactivated influenza vaccines (IIV) or recombinant influenza vaccine (RIV) may be used and is given once each flu season.
Live attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV) should not be used in pregnancy .
Prenatal vaccination affords some temporary protection for infants (Madhi, 2014; Munoz, 2019; Tita, 2016).
The vaccine has not been linked with birth defects or adverse childhood health effects at 5 years of age (Briggs, 2022; Conlin, 2018; Walsh, 2019).
In one case-control study, an association with vaccination and miscarriage was found .
However, the observations were not definite and should not alter clinical practice (Rasmussen, 2019; Sperling, 2018).
Effects on pregnancy outcomes are discussed in more detail in Chapter 67 (p. 1187).
A second coronavirus—Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERSCoV)—originated in Saudi Arabia in 2013.
Fortunately, the epidemic was contained and short lived.
# Coronavirus.
The first coronaviral infection in China in 2002 that caused severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) was termed SARS-CoV.
It caused atypical pneumonitis with a case-fatality rate of approximately 10 percent .
SARS in pregnancy had a case-fatality rate of up to 40 percent .
Ng and associates (2006) reported that the placentas from 7 of 19 cases showed abnormal intervillous or subchorionic fibrin deposition in three, and extensive fetal thrombotic vasculopathy in two.
In the winter of 2019–2020, a second worldwide outbreak of a genetically similar virus originated in China.
This was Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV2) known as COVID-19.
Illness severity ranges from mild common-cold symptoms to severe pneumonia or acute respiratory distress syndrome .
From 18 affected pregnancies, the clinical course of COVID-19 is similar to that seen in nonpregnant women.
However, preterm labor appears to be an associated risk (Chen, 2020; Zhu, 2020).
To minimize transmission of COVID-19, inpatient guidelines recommend caring for an affected patient in a negative-pressure airborne infection isolation room (AIIR) or transfer to an equipped facility.
The potential for vertical transmission (mother–to–newborn) transmission is currently unclear Breslin, 2020).
Neonates are suspected to have infection.
Thus, isolation of the newborn from other neonates is recommended.
A newborn may room in with its mother, who practices hand hygiene and wears a mask (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2020).
# Varicella Pneumonia.
Infection with varicella-zoster virus, the same agent responsible for chickenpox, results in pneumonitis in 5 percent of gravidas .
Diagnosis and management are considered in Chapter 67 (p. 1186).
# Pneumocystis Pneumonia.
Fungal and yeast infections are usually of greatest consequence in immunocompromised hosts, especially in women with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).
Of these, lung infection with Pneumocystis jirovecii, formerly called Pneumocystis carinii, is a common complication.
The opportunistic yeast-like fungus causes interstitial pneumonia characterized by dry cough, tachypnea, dyspnea, and diffuse radiographic infiltrates.
This organism is identified by polymerase chain reaction testing of bronchoalveolar lavage secretions or, when necessary, tissue staining of biopsy specimens .
More common in HIVinfected persons, its
incidence has risen in other immunocompromised groups .
In a report from the AIDS Clinical Trials Centers, pneumocystis pneumonia was the most frequent HIV-related disorder in pregnant women .
Ahmad and associates (2001) reviewed 22 cases during pregnancy and cited a 50-percent mortality rate.
Treatment is with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for 14 to 21 days.
Alternative agents include sulfadiazine plus pyrimethamine.
Glucocorticoids also improve survival rates.
Echinocandins have been used successfully in nonpregnant patients .
Tracheal intubation and mechanical ventilation may be required in some cases.
For prophylaxis, several international health agencies recommend one double-strength trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole tablet orally daily for certain groups of HIV-infected pregnant women.
These include women with CD4+ Tlymphocyte counts <200/μL, those whose CD4+ T lymphocytes constitute <14 percent, or if there is an AIDS-defining illness, particularly oropharyngeal candidiasis .
# Fungal Pneumonia.
Any of several fungi can cause pneumonia.
In pregnancy, this is usually seen in women with HIV infection or other sources of immunocompromise.
In uncompromised women, infection is usually mild and self-limited.
It is characterized initially by cough and fever, and dissemination is infrequent .
Histoplasmosis and blastomycosis do not appear to be more frequent or more severe during pregnancy .
Data concerning coccidioidomycosis are conflicting (Bercovitch, 2011; Patel, 2013).
In a case-control study from an endemic area, pregnancy was a significant risk factor for disseminated disease .
In another study, however, Caldwell and coworkers (2000) identified 32 serologically confirmed cases during pregnancy and documented dissemination in only three.
Women with associated erythema nodosum have a better prognosis, whereas mediastinal lymphadenopathy may more likely reflect disseminated disease .
Last, Crum and Ballon-Landa (2006) reviewed 80 cases of antepartum coccidioidomycosis and found that almost all women diagnosed in the third trimester had disseminated disease.
Although the overall maternal mortality rate was 40 percent, it was 20 percent for 29 cases reported since 1973.
Spinello (2007) and Bercovitch (2011) with their colleagues provide reviews of coccidioidomycosis in pregnancy.
Most cases of cryptococcosis reported during pregnancy manifest as meningitis.
Otherwise healthy pregnant women occasionally have cryptococcal pneumonia .
Diagnosis is difficult because clinical presentation is similar to that of other community-acquired pneumonias.
Itraconazole is the preferred therapy for most disseminated fungal infections .
Pregnant women have also been given IV amphotericin B or ketoconazole (Lewis, 2018; Paranyuk, 2006; Pilmis, 2015).
Amphotericin B has been used extensively in pregnancy with no embryofetal effects.
Early in pregnancy, fluconazole and ketoconazole may be embryotoxic in large doses.
In the first trimester, these two and itraconazole are ideally avoided if possible .
Three echinocandin derivatives—caspofungin, micafungin, and anidulafungin—are effective for invasive candidiasis .
They are embryotoxic and teratogenic in laboratory animals and use in human pregnancies has not been reported .
Tuberculosis.
It is estimated that a third of the world population is infected with Mycobacterium tuberculosis .
In the United States, it is uncommon and is a disease of the elderly, the urban poor, minority groups, and patients with HIV infection .
According to the CDC (2019b), the incidence of active tuberculosis in this country has plateaued since 2000, and immigrants account for more than half of active cases.
Individuals born in the United States have newly acquired infection, whereas foreign-born persons usually have reactivation of latent infection.
Infection begins with inhalation of mycobacteria, which incites a granulomatous pulmonary reaction.
In >90 percent of patients, infection is contained and is dormant for long periods .
In those who are immunocompromised, tuberculosis becomes reactivated to
cause clinical disease.
Active disease manifests usually as cough with minimal sputum production, low-grade fever, hemoptysis, and weight loss.
Various infiltrative patterns are seen on chest radiograph, and cavitation or mediastinal lymphadenopathy may be associated.
Stained smears of sputum reveal acid-fast bacilli (AFB) in approximately two thirds of culturepositive individuals.
Forms of extrapulmonary tuberculosis include lymphadenitis, pleural, genitourinary, skeletal, meningeal, gastrointestinal, and miliary or disseminated .
Silent endometrial tuberculosis can cause tubal infertility .
# Tuberculosis and Pregnancy.
The considerable influx of women into the United States from Asia, Africa, Mexico, and Central America has been accompanied by an increased frequency of tuberculosis in pregnancy.
The prevalence of tuberculosis was 7.1 cases per 100,000 pregnancy-related hospitalizations .
Sackoff and associates (2006) reported positive tuberculin test results in half of 678 foreign-born women attending prenatal clinics in New York City.
At Jackson Memorial Hospital in Miami, 21 percent of 207 pregnant women with HIV infection had a positive skin test result .
One review of 3384 pregnant women showed that 72 percent of active disease is pulmonary .
It also confirmed earlier studies that showed greater adverse maternal and perinatal outcomes .
Others have found similar untoward effects (Dennis, 2018; El-Messidi, 2016).
From her review, Efferen (2007) cited twofold greater rates of low birthweight, preterm delivery, and preeclampsia.
The perinatal mortality rate was almost tenfold higher.
Conversely, treated tuberculosis is usually associated with good pregnancy outcomes (Moro, 2018; Taylor, 2013).
Table 54-6.
Adverse Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes in 3384 Pregnancies Complicated by Active Tuberculosis Extrapulmonary tuberculosis is less common, although its incidence appears to be rising .
Llewelyn and colleagues (2000) reported that 9 of 13 pregnant women with extrapulmonary disease had delayed diagnoses.
In the review cited above, 5.8 percent of women had extrapulmonary infections, and they had worse outcomes .
Jana and coworkers (1999) described outcomes in 33 pregnant women with renal, intestinal, and skeletal tuberculosis, and a third had low-birthweight newborns.
Prevost and Fung Kee Fung (1999) reviewed 56 cases of tuberculous meningitis in which a third of mothers died.
Spinal tuberculosis may cause paraplegia, but vertebral fusion may prevent it from becoming permanent .
Psoas abscess develops in 5 percent of those with spinal infections .
Other presentations include widespread intraperitoneal tuberculosis simulating ovarian carcinomatosis or degenerating leiomyoma, and hyperemesis gravidarum stemming from tubercular meningitis (Kutlu, 2007; Moore, 2008; Sherer, 2005).
# Diagnosis.
For latent tuberculosis, two testing types are used.
One is the time-honored tuberculin skin test (TST), and the others are interferon-gamma release assays (IGRAs), which are becoming preferred (Lewinsohn, 2017; Sosa, 2019).
IGRAs are blood tests that measure interferon-gamma release in response to antigens present in M tuberculosis but not in bacille CalmetteGuérin (BCG) vaccine.
The alternative is skin testing, for which the preferred antigen is purified protein derivative (PPD) of intermediate strength of 5 tuberculin units.
If the intracutaneously applied test result is negative, no further evaluation is needed.
A positive skin test result measures ≥5 mm in diameter and requires evaluation for active disease, including a chest radiograph.
For active infection, nucleic acid amplification testing and mycobacterial culture is recommended .
Clinicians should promptly contact their state health department for cases of suspected or confirmed active tuberculosis.
Health departments can assist in providing patient and public health management.
This often includes directly observed therapy (DOT) to ensure regimen compliance .
Each state’s control office can be found at www.cdc.gov/tb/links/tboffices.htm.
# Treatment.
Latent
Infection In nonpregnant, tuberculin-positive patients younger than 35 years with no evidence of active disease, treatment is given to substantially reduce the risk that their latent infection will progress to active disease.
The preferred therapy is one of three rifamycin-based regimens with or without isoniazid for 3 to 4 months duration .
Alternatively, isoniazid, 300 mg orally daily, is given for 6 to 9 months.
Isoniazid has been used for decades, and it is considered safe in pregnancy (Briggs, 2022; Moro, 2018).
However, for gravidas with latent infection, most recommend that isoniazid therapy be delayed until after delivery .
Some even recommend withholding treatment until 3 to 6 months after delivery because of a possibly increased isoniazid-induced hepatitis risk in postpartum women.
Serum levels of hepatic transaminases should be monitored with isoniazid therapy.
Compliance is a major problem with postpartum therapy.
Only 10 to 18 percent of postpartum patients complete treatment (Cruz, 2005; Sackoff, 2006).
One obvious disconnect is that care for tuberculosis is given in health systems apart from prenatal care .
In a decision model, Boggess and colleagues (2000) reported fewer cases of tuberculosis if treatment for a positive tuberculin skin test result occurred antepartum.
There are exceptions to delayed treatment for latent infection in pregnancy.
Recent skin test convertors are treated antepartum because the incidence of active infection is 5 percent in the first year .
Skin-test-positive women exposed to active infection are also treated because the incidence of infection is 0.5 percent per year.
Last, women with HIV infection are treated because they have an approximate 10-percent annual risk of active disease.
Active Infection Regimens.
Resistance to antituberculosis drugs has led to emergence of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) strains.
The World Health Organization (2017) recommends isoniazid, rifampin, ethambutol, and pyrazinamide together for 6 months for nonpregnant persons.
These are used until susceptibility studies are performed .
Pyridoxine is added to help prevent isoniazid-associated neuropathy.
A newer 4-month isoniazid, rifapentine, moxifloxacin, and pyrazinamide regimen was not inferior to the standard one .
During pregnancy, in the first 2-month bactericidal phase, isoniazid, rifampin, and ethambutol are given.
This is followed by a 7-month continuation phase with isoniazid and rifampin .
A few reports describe MDR-TB during pregnancy, and treatment options have been reviewed .
Treatment should be undertaken in consultation with infectious disease and the local health department.
Breastfeeding is not prohibited during antituberculous therapy.
If neonatal therapy is indicated, medication levels in breast milk are inadequate for this.
Treatment of active disease is of special concern in HIV-infected women who are antiretroviral naïve.
In these circumstances, beginning concomitant therapy with antituberculosis and antiretroviral therapy can cause the immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome (IRIS) with toxic drug effects .
That said, some studies support administration of antiretroviral therapy 2 to 4 weeks after beginning antituberculosis therapy (Blanc, 2011; Havlir, 2011).
Also, rifampin or rifabutin may be contraindicated if certain protease inhibitors or nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors are used.
If there is resistance to rifabutin or rifampin, then pyrazinamide therapy is given.
Of the second-line regimens, the aminoglycosides—streptomycin, kanamycin, amikacin, and capreomycin —are ototoxic to the fetus and are contraindicated .
Transmission Prevention.
Inpatient airborne precautions should be initiated for any patient with suspected active pulmonary tuberculosis or for patients who remain infectious despite treatment.
Precautions include rooming in a negative-pressure room.
Patients are encouraged to wear surgical masks during interactions, and health-care workers should don personally fitted N95 respirator masks.
Patients undergoing treatment can be
considered noninfectious: (1) after 2 weeks of DOT treatment compliance, (2) after three consecutive AFB-negative sputum smears, or (3) after clinical improvement evidenced by absent fever and resolving cough .
Neonatal Tuberculosis Tuberculous bacillemia can infect the placenta, but the fetus infrequently becomes infected.
Congenital tuberculosis applies also to newborns who are infected by aspiration of infected secretions at delivery.
Each route constitutes approximately half of the cases.
Neonatal tuberculosis simulates other congenital infections and manifests with hepatosplenomegaly, respiratory distress, fever, and lymphadenopathy .
Cantwell and colleagues (1994) reviewed 29 cases of congenital tuberculosis.
Only 12 of the mothers had active infection, and tuberculosis was frequently demonstrated by postpartum endometrial biopsy.
Adhikari and associates (1997) described 11 South African postpartum women whose endometrial biopsy was culture-positive.
Six of their neonates had congenital tuberculosis.
Neonatal infection is unlikely if the mother with active disease is treated before delivery or if her sputum culture is negative.
Most experts recommend isolation of the susceptible newborn from the mother suspected of having active disease.
If the mother is infectious, 3 to 6 months of isoniazid prophylaxis is given to the newborn.
In an older study, the risk of disease in the untreated infant born to a woman with active infection was 50 percent in the first year .
Sarcoidosis.
This is a chronic, multisystem inflammatory disease of unknown etiology characterized by an accumulation of T-helper lymphocytes and phagocytes within noncaseating granulomas (Baughman, 2018; Spagnolo, 2018).
Predisposition to the disease is genetically determined and characterized by an exaggerated response of helper T lymphocytes to environmental triggers.
Pulmonary involvement is most common, followed by skin, eyes, lymph nodes, and then all other organ systems.
The prevalence of sarcoid in the United States is 20 to 60 cases per 100,000, with equal sex distribution.
It is more than 10 times more common for blacks than for whites.
Most patients are between 20 and 40 years at disease presentation.
Pulmonary symptoms are dominant, and more than 90 percent of patients have an abnormal chest radiograph at some point.
Interstitial pneumonitis is the hallmark of pulmonary involvement, and half of affected patients develop permanent radiological changes.
Lymphadenopathy, especially of the mediastinum, is present in 75 to 90 percent of cases.
A third each have uveitis and skin involvement, the latter usually manifest as erythema nodosum.
In women, sarcoid causes approximately 10 percent of cases of erythema nodosum .
Importantly, any other organ system may be involved.
Confirmation of the diagnosis is with biopsy—preferably a lymph node.
However, because the lung may be the only obviously involved organ, tissue acquisition is often difficult.
The overall prognosis for sarcoidosis is good, and it resolves without treatment in 50 percent of patients.
Still, quality of life is diminished, and in 20 percent chronic organ dysfunction, albeit mild and nonprogressive, persists .
Approximately 5 percent die because of their disease.
Glucocorticoids are the most widely used treatment for symptomatic disease.
Permanent organ derangement is seldom reversed by their use .
Thus, the decision to treat is based on symptoms, physical findings, chest radiograph, and pulmonary function tests.
Unless respiratory symptoms are prominent, therapy is usually withheld for a several-month observation period.
If inflammation does not subside, prednisone, 20 to 40 mg/d, is given daily and tapered to <10 mg by 6 months .
For those with an inadequate response, immunosuppressive or cytotoxic agents and cytokine modulators can be used.
# Sarcoidosis and Pregnancy.
Because it is uncommon and frequently benign, sarcoidosis is not often diagnosed in pregnancy.
In a study of the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, the incidence was 9.6 cases per 100,000 births .
Meningitis, heart
failure, and neurosarcoidosis complicating pregnancy have been described (Cardonick, 2000; Maisel, 1996; Wallmüller, 2012).
Many small studies report benign associations between sarcoidosis and pregnancy.
However, Table 54-7.
displays the increased incidences of both maternal and fetal adverse outcomes found in a Nationwide Inpatient Sample study of 678 cases .
Risks for preeclampsia and preterm delivery were approximately twofold greater.
Risks for eclampsia, deep-vein thrombosis, and pulmonary embolism were five- to sevenfold higher.
TABLE 54-7.
Maternal and Perinatal Adverse Outcomes in 678 Women with Sarcoidosis Active sarcoidosis is treated using the same guidelines as for nongravid women.
Severe disease warrants serial pulmonary function determination.
Symptomatic uveitis, constitutional symptoms, and pulmonary symptoms are treated with prednisone.
Cystic Fibrosis.
# Pathophysiology.
Cystic fibrosis is an autosomal recessive exocrinopathy and is one of the most common fatal genetic disorders in Caucasians.
Cystic fibrosis is caused by one of more than 2000 mutations in a 230-kb gene on the long arm of chromosome 7 .
The normal peptide gene product functions as a chloride channel and is termed the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR).
Mutations in the chloride channel alters epithelial transport of electrolytes in CFTR-secretory cells.
Affected sites include the sinuses, lung, pancreas, liver, and reproductive tract.
Exocrine gland ductal obstruction develops from thick, viscid secretions.
In the lung, submucosal glandular ducts are affected.
Eccrine sweat gland abnormalities are the basis for the diagnostic sweat test, characterized by elevated sodium, potassium, and chloride levels in sweat.
Lung involvement is commonplace and is usually the cause of death.
Bronchial gland hypertrophy with mucous plugging and small-airway obstruction leads to subsequent infection that ultimately causes chronic bronchitis and bronchiectasis.
For complex and not completely explicable reasons, chronic inflammation is caused by Pseudomonas aeruginosa, S aureus, and H influenzae.
Acute and chronic parenchymal inflammation ultimately causes extensive fibrosis, and along with airway obstruction, ventilation–perfusion mismatch develops.
Pulmonary insufficiency is the end result.
Currently, the median predicted survival is 37 years, and nearly 80 percent of females with cystic fibrosis now survive to adulthood .
As discussed in Chapter 17 (p. 342), phenotypes vary widely, even among homozygotes for the common Phe508del (∆F508) mutation.
Disease severity depends on which two alleles are inherited, and approximately 10 percent are disease-causing mutations .
Homozygosity for ∆F508 is one of the most severe, and 90 percent of individuals with clinical disease carry at least one F508 allele.
# Preconceptional Counseling.
Women with clinical cystic fibrosis are subfertile because of tenacious cervical mucus.
Traxler and colleagues (2019) recommend in-depth preconceptional counseling regarding contraception.
Males have oligospermia or aspermia from associated congenital bilateral absence of the vas deferens (CBAVD), and 98 percent are infertile .
Despite this, the North American Cystic Fibrosis Foundation estimated that 4 percent of affected women become pregnant every year .
The endometrium and tubes express some CFTR but are functionally normal, and the ovaries do not express the CFTR gene.
Both intrauterine insemination and in vitro fertilization can be successful for affected women.
Important factors are the long-term prognosis for the parent(s) and mutation transmission to their offspring.
Screening The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020) recommends that carrier screening be offered to all women, affected by cystic fibrosis or not, who are currently pregnant or considering conception .
The CDC also added cystic fibrosis to newborn screening programs .
The CFTR2 website (www.cftr2.org) helps delineate which gene variants have a clear diseasecausing role and which are benign mutations.
#
Prenatal Care.
Pregnancy outcome is inversely related to severity of lung dysfunction.
Advanced chronic lung disease, hypoxia, and frequent infections may prove deleterious.
At least in the past, cor pulmonale was common, but even that does not preclude successful pregnancy .
In some women, pancreatic dysfunction may cause malnutrition.
Approximately 10 percent have pregestational diabetes .
Otherwise normal pregnancyinduced insulin resistance frequently results in gestational diabetes after midpregnancy.
In one study of 48 pregnancies, half had pancreatic insufficiency, and a third required insulin .
Cystic fibrosis is not affected by pregnancy.
Early reports of a deleterious effect on the course of cystic fibrosis were related to severe disease .
When matched with nonpregnant women by disease severity, some reports indicate no deleterious effects on long-term survival .
# Management.
Prepregnancy counseling is imperative.
Women who choose to become pregnant require close surveillance for development of superimposed infection, diabetes, and heart failure.
Serial pulmonary function testing assists management and estimates prognosis.
If the FEV1 is at least 50 percent, women usually tolerate pregnancy well .
Emphasis is placed on postural drainage, bronchodilator therapy, and infection control.
β-Adrenergic bronchodilators help control airway constriction.
Inhaled recombinant human deoxyribonuclease I improves lung function by reducing sputum viscosity .
Inhaled 7-percent saline produces shortand long-term benefits.
Nutritional status is assessed, and appropriate dietary counseling given.
Calcium and vitamin D are given for poor bone mineralization.
Pancreatic insufficiency requires replacement of oral pancreatic enzymes.
Promising new therapy to correct CFTR protein dysfunction has been recently described.
Using a combination of “CFTR correctors” (tezacaftor–ivacaftor congeners), patients homozygous for the Phe508del mutation significantly benefitted (Davies, 2018; Keating, 2018).
No reports of these drugs are available regarding pregnant women.
Infection is heralded by increasing cough and mucus production.
Oral semisynthetic penicillins or cephalosporins usually suffice to treat staphylococcal infections.
Pseudomonas infection is problematic, and inhaled tobramycin and colistin have been used successfully to control this organism.
Serious pulmonary infections are treated with immediate hospitalization and aggressive therapy.
The threshold for hospitalization with other complications is low.
For labor and delivery, epidural analgesia is recommended .
# Pregnancy Outcome.
Earlier reports chronicled the poor maternal and perinatal outcomes in affected women (Cohen, 1980; Kent, 1993).
More recent reports describe better outcomes, but there still are serious complications (Schlüter, 2019).
Disease severity is now quantified by pulmonary function studies, which are the best predictor of pregnancy and long-term maternal outcome.
One report of 69 pregnancies found that if prepregnancy FEV1 was <60 percent of predicted, the risk for preterm delivery, respiratory complications, and death of the mother within a few years of childbirth was substantive .
Others report similar findings (Fitzsimmons, 1996; Thorpe-Beeston, 2013).
Of 75 pregnancies from the French Cystic Fibrosis Registry, almost 20 percent of newborns were delivered preterm, and 30 percent had growth restriction .
The one maternal death was due to Pseudomonas sepsis in a woman whose prepregnancy FEV1 was 60 percent.
Long-term, however, 17 percent of women died, and four infants had confirmed cystic fibrosis.
Meconium peritonitis is found in 10 to 20 percent of affected fetuses (Boczar, 2015; Terlizzi, 2016).
In a more recent report from the French registry, women with pregestational diabetes had outcomes similar to those without diabetes .
Patel and associates (2015) queried the National Inpatient Sample database and reported that the prevalence of cystic fibrosis in pregnancy had a significant linear rise from 2000 to 2010.
They analyzed 1119 affected
women and reported a litany of risks .
In contrast, perinatal outcomes were surprisingly good.
Table 54-8.
Odds Ratios for Maternal Complications in 1119 Pregnant Women with Cystic Fibrosis Compared with Controls # Lung Transplantation.
Cystic fibrosis is a common antecedent disease leading to lung transplantation.
Gyi and coworkers (2006) reviewed 10 pregnancies in women following transplantation and reported nine liveborn neonates.
Maternal outcomes were less favorable.
Of the three gravidas who developed rejection during pregnancy, all had progressively declining pulmonary function and died of chronic rejection by 38 months after delivery.
More recent international data show a median survival of 10.5 years in patients living beyond the first year .
Carbon Monoxide Poisoning.
Carbon monoxide is a ubiquitous gas, and most nonsmoking adults have a carbon monoxyhemoglobin saturation of 1 to 3 percent.
In cigarette smokers, levels may be 5 to 15 percent, and polycythemia is comorbid.
Carbon monoxide is the most frequent cause of poisoning worldwide .
Toxic levels are often encountered in inadequately ventilated areas warmed by space heaters.
Carbon monoxide is particularly toxic because it is odorless and tasteless and has a high affinity for hemoglobin binding.
Thus, it displaces oxygen and impedes its transfer with resultant hypoxia.
Besides acute sequelae including death and anoxic encephalopathy, cognitive defects develop in as many as half of patients following loss of consciousness or in those with carbon monoxide levels >25 percent .
Hypoxic brain damage has a predilection for the cerebral cortex and white matter and for the basal ganglia (Lo, 2007; Prockop, 2007).
A Parkinson syndrome sometimes follows after recovery.
# Pregnancy and Carbon Monoxide Poisoning.
Through several physiological alterations, the rate of endogenous carbon monoxide production almost doubles in normal pregnancy .
Although the pregnant woman is not more susceptible to carbon monoxide poisoning, the fetus does not tolerate excessive exposure (Friedman, 2015; Nowadly, 2018).
With chronic exposure, maternal symptoms usually appear when the carboxyhemoglobin concentration is 5 to 20 percent.
Symptoms include headache, weakness, dizziness, physical and visual impairment, palpitations, and nausea and vomiting.
With acute exposure, concentrations of 30 to 50 percent produce symptoms of impending cardiovascular collapse.
Levels >50 percent may be fatal for the mother.
Because hemoglobin F has an even higher affinity for carbon monoxide, fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels are 10 to 15 percent higher than those in the mother.
This may be due to facilitated diffusion .
Importantly, the half-life of carboxyhemoglobin is 2 hours in the mother but 7 hours in the fetus.
Carbon monoxide is bound so tightly to hemoglobin F, the fetus may be hypoxic even before maternal carbon monoxide levels are appreciably elevated.
Several anomalies are associated with embryonic exposure, and anoxic encephalopathy is the primary sequela of later fetal exposure (Alehan, 2007; Nowadly, 2018).
# Treatment.
For all victims, treatment of carbon monoxide poisoning is supportive along with immediate administration of 100-percent inspired oxygen.
Indications for hyperbaric oxygen treatment in nonpregnant individuals are unclear .
Weaver and associates (2002) reported that hyperbaric oxygen treatment minimized the incidence of cognitive defects in adults at both 6 weeks and 1 year compared with normobaric oxygen.
Hyperbaric oxygen is generally recommended in pregnancy if carbon monoxide exposure has been “significant” (Aubard, 2000; Ernst, 1998).
The problem is how to define significant exposure .
Although maternal carbon monoxide levels are not accurately predictive of those in the fetus, some clinicians recommend hyperbaric therapy if maternal levels exceed 15 to 20 percent.
Towers and Corcoran (2009) described affected fetuses to have an elevated baseline heart rate, diminished variability, and absent accelerations and decelerations with fetal monitoring.
Treatment of
the affected newborn with hyperbaric oxygen also is controversial .
Elkharrat and coworkers (1991) described successful hyperbaric treatments in 44 pregnant women.
In another report, a woman’s abnormal neurological and cardiopulmonary findings abated in a parallel fashion with resolution of associated fetal heart rate variable decelerations .
Greingor and coworkers (2001) used 2.5-atm hyperbaric 100-percent oxygen for 90 minutes in a 21-week-pregnant woman who was delivered of a healthy neonate at term.
The Undersea and Hyperbaric Medical Society (2021) has a list of accredited facilities.